Preliminary Inventory to the Michal Sokolnicki Papers, 1908-1968
Hoover Institution Archives
Michal Sokolnicki Papers
1908-1968
68003
Hoover Institution Archives
15 manuscript boxes, 10 microfilm reels (7.8 linear feet)
Diaries, correspondence, writings, dispatches, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to the Polish nationalist movement before and during World War I, Polish relations with Denmark and Turkey, and the Polish Government- in-Exile during World War II. In part, microfilm of originals located in the Pilsudski Institute of America. Original material held at Hoover also available on microfilm (20 reels).
Sokolnicki, Michal, 1880-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Original Materials
In part, microfilm from originals located in the Pilsudski Institute of America.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (20 reels).
Scope and Contents note
Diaries, correspondence, writings, dispatches, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to the Polish nationalist movement before and during World War I, Polish relations with Denmark and Turkey, and the Polish Government- in-Exile during World War II. In part, microfilm of originals located in the Pilsudski Institute of America.
Denmark--Foreign relations--Poland.; Denmark.; Diplomats--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Denmark.; Poland--Foreign relations--Turkey.; Poland--History--20th century.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland.; Turkey--Foreign relations--Poland.; Turkey.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Polish Legation in Kopenhagen: correspondence of Minister Michal Sokolnicki with Cardinal August Hlond, 1932-1935. (Box 1)
- Diplomatic correspondence and reports of Michal Sokolnicki as Ambassador in Turkey, and followin folders:, May 1935 - December 1940
  - Reports from the Polish diplomatic posts in Washington, London, Stockholm and Lisbon, April 1938 - July 1939.
  - Ambassador's dispatches to the Ministry of Foreign Affair in Warsaw, April 1938 - August 31, 1939.
  - Reports from Ambassador Roger Raczynski, Bucarest, September 15-30, 1939.
  - Correspondence with Ambassador Roger Raczynski, 1940-1941
- Diplomatic correspondence and reports, January 1942 - December 1943. (Box 2)
  - Correspondence relating to the Polish-Soviet agreement of, July 1941.
  - Correspondence with General Anders, 1943 - 1944.
  - Correspondence with General Sikorski; Conference in Beyreuth, June 1943.
  - Katyn. The mass murder of Polish prisoners of war; Reports.
  - Hungary's political position, 1939 - 1943.
  - Polish-Soviet relations: documents, by Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs, London., April 1943 - August 1946
- Diplomatic correspondence and reports, Folders:, January 1944 - August 1945. (Box 3)
  - Warsaw uprising, August 1944.
  - Lublin Committee, 1944.
  - Yalta Conference, February 1945.
  - Trials of Polish underground leaders, Moscow, June 1945.
  - Turkish-Soviet relations, 1944-1945.
  - Recognition of Polish Provisional Government by Turkey.
  - List of Polish diplomatic posts active in, 1945.
  - Adampol, 1945.
  - Correspondence with Ambassador Alfred Poninski, 1942-44.
- Correspondence, notes, Folders:, January 1946 - December 1951. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence with Minister of Foreign Affairs in London, May 1947-Nov. 1948.
  - Liquidation of the Polish Armed Forces - documents, Military Commission of the Government-in-Exile, London., 1945-1946
  - Documents relating to the eve of the Second World War, New Ti, April, 1948.
  - Correspondence with the Institute of the Near and Middle East Reduta, 1948-1950.
  - Correspondence with Patriarch Athenagoras, Istanbul, 1948-1949
  - Komunizm - dokumentacja miesiczna, London., 1948-1949.
- Correspondence, notes, Folders:, January 1952 - December 1960; 1961-1968. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with General Marian Kukiel, 1953-1963.
  - Correspondence with editors of Kultura, 1953-1954.
  - Correspondence with Pobog-Malinowski.
  - Correspondence with Archbishop J.F.Gawlina, 1959-1960.
  - Correspondence with J.Fryling, 1951-1952.
  - Correspondence with Klaudiusz Hrabyk, 1954-1955.
- Ambassador Sokolnicki's Diary, September 1, 1939 - August 1945.; Manuscript. (Box 6-8)
- Manuscript of Josef Beck's Commentary of the diplomatic history of the war of 1939. Dictated in Bucarest in published in New York in as Final report., March 1943, 1957 (Box 9)
- Ambassador's Ankara Diary - first draft of the abridged version of his wartime diary.
- Introduction a l'histoire diplomatic - Sokolnicki's lectures at the History Department of Ankara University, 1952.
- Poland 1914-1945, collective work, which was to be published in United States. Manuscripts of the chapters written by Michal Sokolnicki. (Box 10)
- Manuscripts of Sokolnicki's articles which appeared in in Bellona, Kultura, Wiadomosci, Orzel Bialy, Dziennik Polski i Dziennik Zolnierza., 1955-1960
- Political history of the Second World War, 1939-1945, manuscript and relating correspondence, 1956-58. (Box 11)
  - Unpublished articles, notes and research material.
- Writings and research material. Folders: (Box 12)
  - Nienapisana ksika - Rebirth of the Polish Republic, 1919-1926.
  - Na prezeomie polityki legionowej. Epizody roku 1916.
  - Polish-Finnish question article and related correspondence.
- Copies of Polish emigré publications, London, Folders:, 1947-1953. (Box 13)
  - Biuletyn Instytutu Bada Krajowych.
  - Biuletyn Ligi Niepodlegoci Polski.
  - Wiadomoci Krajowe.
  - Egzekutywa Zjednoczenia Nàrodowego.
  - Biuletyn P lskiej Agencji Telegraficznej.
  - Biuletyn Polityczny.
  - Wschód Polski - and other publications of emigre organizations.
- Research material - newspapers clippings relating to the Second World War, Polish-Russian relations, Turkey and Balkan countries (Box 14)
- Newspapers clippings relating to the Second World War, from Polish, Russian, French and British newspapers. (Box 15)
- Microfilm reels of Michal Sokolnicki papers held at the Pilsudski Institute of America (Reels 1-10)